I've been living in rural East Africa for about 10 years,
اعيش في ريف شرق افريقيا منذ حوالي 10 سنوات
and I want to share a field perspective with you on global poverty.
وأريد أن أشارككم منظوري العملي للفقر العالمى
I believe that the greatest failure of the human race
انا أؤمن بأن فشل الجنس البشري الاعظم
is the fact that we've left more than one billion of our members behind.
يكمن بحقيقة تركنا لاكثر من بليون انسان منا وراء ظهورنا
Hungry, extreme poverty:
الجوع, والفقر الشديد:
these often seem like gigantic, insurmountable problems,
عادة ما تبدو هذه كمشكلات ضخمة ومستعصية
too big to solve.
اضخم من ان يكون لها حل
But as a field practitioner,
ولكن كممارس بالميدان،
I believe these are actually very solvable problems
اعتقد بانها مشكلات ذات قابلية عالية للحل
if we just take the right strategies.
فقط ان اتبعنا الاستراتيجيات الصحيحة.
Archimedes was an ancient Greek thinker,
قد كان ارخميدس أحد المفكرين الاغريق القدامى
and he taught us that if we lean on the right levers,
علمنا أنه إن أتكلناعلى العتلات الصحيحة
we can move the world.
نستطيع تحريك العالم.
In the fight against extreme poverty, I believe there are three powerful levers
أنا اؤمن أنه فى نضالنا ضد الفقر المدقع هنالك ثلاث عتلات قوية
that we can lean on.
نستطيع الاتكاء عليها.
This talk is all about those levers, and why they make poverty
هذا الحديث عن تلك العتلات وكيفية جعلها الفقر
a winnable fight in our lifetimes.
نضال قابل للنصرفي حياتنا
What is extreme poverty?
ما هو الفقر المدقع؟
When I first moved to rural East Africa,
في بداية انتقالي إلى ريف أفريقيا الشرقية
I stayed overnight with a farm family.
مكثت ليلا مع عائلة ريفية.
They were wonderful people.
وكانوا أناسا رائعين.
They invited me into their home. We sang songs together
وقد دعونى إلى منزلهم وغنينا سويا.
and ate a simple dinner.
وتناولنا عشاءا بسيطا
They gave me a blanket to sleep on the floor.
اعطونى لحافا لأنام على الأرضية.
In the morning, however, there was nothing to eat.
ولكن نهارا لم يكن هناك ما يؤكل.
And then at lunchtime, I watched with an increasingly sick feeling
وقت الغداء شاهدت وانا اشعر بالسقم
as the eldest girl in the family cooked porridge as a substitute for lunch.
الفتاة الكبري وهى تطهو الثريد كغداء
For that meal, every child drank one cup to survive.
لهذه الوجبة يتناول كل طفل كوبا واحا للغداء ليبقى حيا.
And I cannot tell you how ashamed I felt
انا لست قادرا على وصف كم كنت اشعر بالخزى
when they handed one of those cups to me,
عندما اعطونى احد تلك الاكواب،
and I knew I had to accept their hospitality.
وقد علمت أنه يجب على قبول ضيافتهم
Children need food not only to survive but also to grow physically and mentally.
يحتاج الاطفال للطعام ليس للعيش فحسب وانما للنمو العقلى والجسدى ايضا
Every day they fail to eat, they lose a little bit of their future.
كل يوم يوم بلا طعام يفقدون جزءا من مستقبلهم
Amongst the extreme poor, one in three children
واحد من كل ثلاثة اطفال بهذا الفقر المدقع
are permanently stunted from a lifetime of not eating enough.
غير مكتمل النمو نتيجة لحياة من الطعام الضئيل
When that's combined with poor access to health care,
عندما يجتمع هذا وعدم وجود رعاية صحية
one in 10 extremely poor children die before they reach age five.
فانهم يموتون قبل الوصول لسن خمس سنوات.
And only one quarter of children complete high school
ويكمل ربع هؤلاء الاطفال المرحلة الثانوية
because they lack school fees.
لعدم امتلاكهم لمصاريف المدرسة.
Hunger and extreme poverty curb human potential in every possible way.
يكبح الجوع والفقر المدقع القوة الانسانية الكامنة بكل الطرق الممكنة
We see ourselves as a thinking, feeling and moral human race,
نحن نرى انفسنا كجنس بشري مفك ويشعر واخلاقى
but until we solve these problems for all of our members,
ولكن حتى نحل تلك المشاكل للجميع،
we fail that standard,
نحن نفتقر لهذا النموذج.
because every person on this planet matters.
لأن كل شخص بالعالم مهم
This child matters.
هذا الطفل مهم.
These children matter.
هؤلاء الاطفال مهمون.
This girl matters.
تلك الفتاة مهمة.
You know, we see things like this,
نحن نرى اشياء كهذه،
and we're upset by them,
ونستاء من اجلها.
but they seem like such big problems.
ولكنها تبدو كمشاكل كبيرة.
We don't know how to take effective action.
ولا نعلم كيفية اتخاذ قرارا فعالا.
But remember our friend Archimedes.
ولكن تذكر صديقنا ارخميدس.
Global poverty has powerful levers.
للفقر المدقع عتلات قوية.
It's a problem like any other.
وهى مشكلة كغيرها
I live and work in the field, and as a practitioner,
انا اعيش واعمل بالمحال كممارس.
I believe these are very solvable problems.
واؤمن بامكانيه حل تلك المشاكل.
So for the next 10 minutes,
لمدة 10 دقائق،
let's not be sad about the state of the world.
دعونا لانكون مستائين بشأن وضع العالم.
Let's engage our brains.
دعونا نحكم عقولنا،
Let's engage our collective passion for problem-solving
لنحكم شغنا بحل المشكلات.
and figure out what those levers are.
لنعلم ما هى تلك العتلات.
Lever number one: most of the world's poor are farmers.
العتلة الأولى: معظم فقراء العالم فلاحون
Think about how extraordinary this is.
فكر كم هذا غريب.
If this picture represents the world's poor,
ان كانت هذه الصورة تمثل فقراء العالم،
then more than half engage in farming as a major source of income.
اذن فاكثر من نصف العاملين بالزراعة كمصدر اساسي للدخل.
This gets me really excited.
وهذا ما يثير فضولي.
All of these people, one profession.
كل هؤلاء بمهنة واحدة.
Think how powerful this is.
فكر كم هذا قويا.
When farmers become more productive, then more than half the world's poor
عندما ينتج المزارعون أكثر،
earn more money and climb out of poverty.
اصبح نصف العالم فقير.
And it gets better.
اكسب مالا اكثر واخرج من دائرة الفقر.
The product of farming is, of course, food.
وهاهو الوضع يتحسن. فناتج الزراعة هو الطعام بالطبع.
So when farmers become more productive, they earn more food,
وعليه فعندما يصبح الفاحون اكثر انتاجية , يجنون طعاما اكثر
and they don't just help themselves,
و هم لا يساعدون انفسهم فحسب
but they help to feed healthy communities and thriving economies.
ولكنهم يساعدون فى اطعام المجتمعات المزدهرة صحيا واقتصاديا.
And when farmers become more productive, they reduce environmental pressure.
وعندما يصبح الفلاخون أكثر انتاجية، يقللون الضغوط البيئية.
We only have two ways we can feed the world:
لدينا فقط طريقان لإطعام العالم:
we can either make our existing farmland a lot more productive,
إما ان نجعل مزارعنا أكثر انتاجية،
or we can clear cut forest and savannah to make more farmland,
أو ان نقطع الغابات ونستبدلها بالزراعة،
which would be environmentally disastrous.
مما سيشكل كارثة بيئية.
Farmers are basically a really important leverage point.
الفلاحون نقطة تحول رئيسية.
When farmers become more productive,
عندما يصبح الفلاحون أكثر إنتاجية،
they earn more income, they climb out of poverty,
سيجنون مال أكثر، ويتغلبوا على الفقر.
they feed their communities and they reduce environmental land pressure.
يطعموا مجتمعاتهم ويقللوا الضغوط البيئية.
Farmers stand at the center of the world.
يقف الفلاحون في مركز العالم.
And not a farmer like this one,
لكن ليس فلاح مثل هذا.
but rather this lady.
لكن مثل هذه السيدة.
Most of the farmers I know are actually women.
معظم المزارعين الذين اعرفهم سيدات.
Look at the strength and the will radiating from this woman.
انظر الى الطاقة التي تشع من تلك السيدة.
She is physically strong, mentally tough,
هي قوية بدنيا وعقليا،
and she will do whatever it takes to earn a better life for her children.
وستفعل كل ما يلزم لتوفر حياة أفضل لأطفالها
If we're going to put the future of humanity in one person's hands,
لو ينضع مستقبل البشر في يد شخص واحد،
then I'm really glad it's her.
سأكون سعيدا ان تكون هي هذا الشخص.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There's just one problem:
هناك فقك مشكلة واحدة:
many smallholder farmers lack access to basic tools and knowledge.
معظم اصحاب المزارع الصغيرة لا يمتلكون الألات ولا المعرفة الكافية.
Currently, they take a little bit of saved food grain from the prior year,
حاليا، ياخذون بذورا من انتاجية العام الماضي،
they plant it in the ground and they till it with a manual hand hoe.
ليزرعوها في الأرض بالأيدي.
These are tools and techniques that date to the Bronze Age,
تلك الألات التي تعود الي العصر البرونزي،
and it's why many farmers are still very poor.
وهي ما يجعل معظم الفلاحون فقراء.
But good news, again.
لكن هناك خبر جيد.
Lever number two:
العتلة رقم إثنان:
humanity actually solved the problem of agricultural poverty a century ago.
وجد البشر حل لفقر الزراعة منذ قرن.
Let me walk you through the three most basic factors in farming.
لنمر سريعا على الثلاث عناصر الأساسية في الزراعة.
First, hybrid seed is created when you cross two seeds together.
الأولي، البذور المهجنه تنتج عندما تخلط نوعين معا.
If you naturally pollinate a high-yielding variety
لو خلط طبيعيا محصول ذا إنتاجية عالية
together with a drought-resistant variety,
مع محصول ذا مقاومة عالية،
you get a hybrid that inherits positive traits from both of its parents.
ستحصل علي هجين بالصفات الإيجابية في الطرفين.
Next, conventional fertilizer, if used responsibly,
ثانيا، المخصبات، إذا استخدمت بشكل مناسب،
is environmentally sustainable.
ستحافظ على البيئة.
If you micro-dose just a pinch of fertilizer
لو عالجنا المخصبات
to a plant that's taller than I am,
لنبات اطول مني.
you unlock enormous yield gain.
تزداد الإنتاجية بشدة.
These are known as farm inputs.
تلك هي معطيات الزراعة.
Farm inputs need to be combined with good practice.
تلك المعطيات يجب ان تجتمع مع الممارسة
When you space your seeds and plant with massive amounts of compost,
عندما تدع مسافات بين البذور، مع كميات مناسبة من السماد.
farmers multiply their harvests.
تتضاعف المحاصيل.
These proven tools and practices have more than tripled
تلك الأدوات والممارسات
agricultural productivity in every major region of the world,
ضاعفت الانتاجية ثلاث مرات في معظم مناطق العالم،
moving mass numbers of people out of poverty.
واخرجت الكثير من الفقر.
We just haven't finished delivering these things to everybody just yet,
لم نكمل توصيل تلك الأشياء لكل الناس،
particularly in Sub-Saharan Africa.
خصوصا في أفريقا.
So overall, this is amazing news.
في المجمل، هذه أخبار جيدة.
Humanity actually solved agricultural poverty a century ago,
لقد تغلبت البشرية على فقر الزراعة منذ قرن،
in theory.
نظريا.
We just haven't delivered these things to everybody just yet.
نحن فقط لم نوفل هذه الأشياء لكل الناس.
In this century, the reason that people remain poor
في هذه البلد، ما يبقي الناس فقراء
is because maybe they live in remote places.
احتمالية وجودهم في أماكن بعيدة،
They lack access to these things.
قلى الوصول لهذه الأشياء.
Therefore, ending poverty is simply a matter
لذا، التغلب علي الفقر هو مسألة
of delivering proven goods and services to people.
توصيل الادوات والخدمات الخيدة للناس
We don't need more genius types right now.
لا نحتاج حلول عبرقرية الآن.
The humble delivery guy is going to end global poverty in our lifetime.
الشخص المتواضع الذي سيوصل المعلومات سينهي الفقر خلال فترة حياتنا.
So these are the three levers,
حسنا، تلك هي الثلاث عتلات،
and the most powerful lever is simply delivery.
واقوي واحدة هي توفير المعرومات.
Wherever the world's companies, governments and nonprofits
حيثما تقوم الشركات والحكومات والمنظمات التطوعية
set up delivery networks for life-improving goods,
بتوعية الناس عن تطوير الحياة.
we eliminate poverty.
نحن نحد من الفقر.
OK, so that sounds really nice in theory,
حسنا، هذا يبدوا رائعا نظرية،
but what about in practice?
لكن كيف الحال في التطبيق؟
What do these delivery networks look like?
كيف تبدو حملات التوعية تلك؟
I want to share the concrete example that I know best,
اريد ان اشارككم المثار الذي اعرفه جيدا،
my organization, One Acre Fund.
موسستي، (One Acre Fund)
We only serve the farmer,
نحن فقط نساعد الفلاحين،
and our job is to provide her with the tools that she needs to succeed.
ووظيفتنا ان نمدها بالمعدات التي تحتاجها.
We start off by delivering farm inputs to really rural places.
نبدأ بتوفير الإحتياجات للمزارع البعيدة.
Now, this may appear initially very challenging,
هذا يبدو في البداية صعبا.
but it's pretty possible. Let me show you.
لكنه ممكن، دعوني أريكم.
We buy farm inputs with the combined power of our farmer network,
نشتري إحتياجات المزارع
and store it in 20 warehouses like this.
ونخزنهم بعشرين مكان مثل هذا.
Then, during input delivery, we rent hundreds of 10-ton trucks
وعندما نمد الإحتياجات، نحن نؤجر مئات الشاحنات
and send them out to where farmers are waiting in the field.
ونرسلهم للمزارعين.
They then get their individual orders and walk it home to their farms.
يحصل المذارعين علي طلباتهم ويذهبو للمزارع.
It's kind of like Amazon for rural farmers.
مثل أمازون للمزارعين.
Importantly, realistic delivery also includes finance, a way to pay.
وايضا التوصيل يتطلب إيجاد وسيلة للدفع.
Farmers pay us little by little over time, covering most of our expenses.
يدفع الفلاحون لنا جزء جزء مع مرور الوقت، ويغطوا معظم نفقاتنا.
And then we surround all that with training.
ونحيط كل ذلك بالتدريب.
Our rural field officers deliver practical, hands-on training
نقدم تدريب تطبيقي
to farmers in the field
للمزارعين في حقولهم
every two weeks.
كل اسبوعين.
Wherever we deliver our services, farmers use these tools
حيثما نوفر خدماتنا، يقوم المزارعون بإستخدامها
to climb out of poverty.
ليخرجوا من حيز الفقر.
This is a farmer in our program, Consolata.
هذه مزارعة في برنامجنا، كانسولاتا.
Look at the pride on her face.
انظر إالي الفخر في وجهها.
She has achieved a modest prosperity that I believe is the human right
حققت ازدهار طفيف، أمن انه حق
of every hardworking person on the planet.
لكل شخص يعمل بجهد على هذا الكوكب.
Today, I'm proud to say that we're serving about 400,000 farmers like Consolata.
اليوم، انا فخور بأننا نساعد ربعمائة ألف مزارع مثل كونسولاتا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The key to doing this is scalable delivery.
أساس هذا هو التوصيل متغير المدي.
In any given area, we hire a rural field officer
في أي مكان، نعين مسؤول عن المنطقة.
who delivers our services to 200 farmers, on average,
يوصل خدماتنا لمائتي مزارع كمتوسط،
with more than 1,000 people living in those families.
هذا يعني اكثر من الف شخص يعيش فس اسرهم.
Today, we have 2,000 of these rural field officers
اليوم، معنا ألفي مسؤول عن المناطق،
growing very quickly.
والعدد ينمو بسرعة.
This is our delivery army,
هذا هو جيش التوصيل،
and we're just one organization.
ونحن فقط منظمة واحدة.
There are many companies, governments and nonprofits
يوجد العديد من الشركات، والحكومات والمؤسسات الخيرية
that have delivery armies just like this.
التي تلك جيوش لتوصيل الخدمات مثلنا.
And I believe we stand at a moment in time
وأعتقد انا في الوقت الحالي
where collectively, we are capable of delivering farm services to all farmers.
جميعا نمتلك القدرة علي توصيل الخدمات لكل المزارعين.
Let me show you how possible this is.
دعوني اوضح كيف أن هذا ممكن.
This is a map of Sub-Saharan Africa,
هذه خريطة لأفريقيا،
with a map of the United States for scale.
مع خريطة للولايات المتحدة لتوضيح المساحة.
I chose Sub-Saharan Africa because this is a huge delivery territory.
اخترت جنوب أفريقيا لأن هذه منطقة توصيل ضخمة.
It's very challenging.
إنه تحدي صعب.
But we analyzed every 50-mile by 50-mile block on the continent,
قمنا بتحليل كل خمسين ميل على الخريطة.
and we found that half of farmers live in just these shaded regions.
وجدا أن نصف المزارعين يعملون فقط في تلك المنطقة المظللة.
That's a remarkably small area overall.
بشكل ملحوظ هي منطقة صغيرة.
If you were to lay these boxes next to each other
لو ستضع هذه العلامات بجوار بعضها
within a map of the United States,
في خريطة الولايات المتحدة.
they would only cover the Eastern United States.
سيغطوا فقط الجزء الغربي.
You can order pizza anywhere in this territory
يمكنك ان تطلب البيتزا من اي مكان في هذه المنطقة
and it'll arrive to your house hot, fresh and delicious.
وتصلك للمنزل ساخنة وطازجة ولذيذة.
If America can deliver pizza to an area of this size,
لو أمريكا تستطيع توصل البيتزا في أي مكان في هذه المنطقة،
then Africa's companies, governments and non-profits
الشركات الأفريقية والحكومات والمنظمات الخيرية
can deliver farm services to all of her farmers.
يمكن توصيل الخدمات للمزارعين.
This is possible.
هذا ممكن.
I'm going to wrap up by generalizing beyond just farming.
سوف اقوم بتعميم اكبر.
In every field of human development,
في كافة مجالات تطور الإنسان،
humanity has already invented effective tools to end poverty.
أنتجت البشرية وسائل لإنهاء الفقر.
We just need to deliver them.
نحن فقط نريد ان نوفرهم.
So again, in every area of human development,
ثانيا، في كل مجال لنمو الإنسان،
super-smart people a long time ago invented inexpensive,
أشخاص عباقرة أخترعوا معدات رخيصة
highly effective tools.
وعالية الكفائة.
Humanity is armed to the teeth
البشرية معها كل الوسائل
with simple, effective solutions to poverty.
البسيطة والفعالة لحل مشكلة الفقر.
We just need to deliver these to a pretty small area.
نريد فقط ان نوفرهم في امكان صغيرة.
Again using the map of Sub-Saharan Africa as an example,
باستخدام خريطة أريقيا كمثال،
remember that rural poverty is concentrated in these blue shaded areas.
تذكر أن الفقر متمركز في تلك المنطقة الزرقاء،
Urban poverty is even more concentrated, in these green little dots.
الفقر في المدن اكثر عند النقط الخضراء.
Again, using a map of the United States for scale,
بإستخدام خريطة الولايات المتحدة،
this is what I would call a highly achievable delivery zone.
هذا ما أسمية منطقة سهلة التوصيل.
In fact, for the first time in human history,
في الواقع، لأول مرة في التاريخ،
we have a vast amount of delivery infrastructure available to us.
نمتلك اكبر وسائل التوصيل.
The world's companies, governments and non-profits
شركات العالم وحكوماته ومنظماته الخيرية
have delivery armies that are fully capable
تمتلك جيوش للتوصيل قادرة تماما
of covering this relatively small area.
علي تغطية تلك المناطق.
We just lack the will.
نحن فقط نفتقد العزيمة.
If we are willing,
لو نحن مستعدون،
every one of us has a role to play.
لكل منا دور ليلعبه.
We first need more people to pursue careers in human development,
نريد أشخاص أكثر ليبدأوا وظائفهم في مجال تنمية البشر.
especially if you live in a developing nation.
خصوصا لو كنت تعيش في بلد نامي.
We need more front line health workers, teachers, farmer trainers,
نريد اشخاص تعمل على الصحة والتعليم وتدريب المزارعين
sales agents for life-improving goods.
مبيعات السلع التي تنمي المجتمع.
These are the delivery people that dedicate their careers
هؤلاء هم من سيكرسوا حياتهم لتوصيل الأدوات
to improving the lives of others.
التي تطور حياة الأخرين.
But we also need a lot of support roles.
وأيضا نحتاج للكثير من الأدوار المساعدة.
These are roles available at just my organization alone,
هذه الأدوار موجودة في المنظمة التي أعمل بها،
and we're just one out of many.
ونحن منظمة واحدة فقط.
This may surprise you, but no matter what your technical specialty,
هذا قد يدهشك، لكن مهما يكن تخصصك التقني،
there is a role for you in this fight.
يوجد دور لك في هذه المعركة.
And no matter how logistically possible it is to end poverty,
ومها كان القضاء على الفقر متاح،
we need a lot more resources.
مازلنا نحتاج لجهود أكثر.
This is our number one constraint.
هذا هو أساسنا الأول.
For private investors, we need a big expansion of venture capital,
للمثتثمرين، نحتاج رأس مال كبير،
private equity, working capital, available in emerging markets.
عدالة، وأشخاص تعمل في الأسواق الناشئة.
But there are also limits to what private business can accomplish.
ولكن هناك حدود للعمل الحر.
Private businesses often struggle to profitably serve the extreme poor,
يعاني العمر الحر من أن يجني مكسب من خدمة المعدومين،
so philanthropy still has a major role to play.
لذا لدواع تغيير الحياة للأفضل دور كبير.
Anybody can give, but we need more leadership.
كل شخص يمكنه أن يعطي، ولكن نحتاج لقيادة أكبر.
We need more visionary philanthropists
نحتاج لرؤية تخدم رفع المعاناة عن البشر
and global leaders who will take problems in human development
وقادة يواجهوا المشاكل التي تعيق تطور البشر
and lead humanity to wipe them off the face of the planet.
ويقودوا البشر في طريق القضاء عليها.
If you're interested in these ideas, check out this website.
لو كنت مهتم بتلك الفكرة، قم بزيارة هذا الموقع.
We need more leaders.
نحتاج لقادة اكثر.
Humanity has put people on the moon.
البشر وصلوا للقمر.
We've invented supercomputers that fit into our pockets
صنعنا حواسيب فائقة بأحجام صغيرة
and connect us with anybody on the planet.
وتربطنا بأي شخص على الأرض.
We've run marathons at a five-minute mile pace.
ونجري المارثون بسرعة خمسة أميال في الدقيقة.
We are an exceptional people.
نحن أشخاص استثنائين
But we've left more than one billion of our members behind.
لكننا تركنا اكثل من بليون شخص خلف ظهورنا.
Until every girl like this one has an opportunity
حتي تحصل كل فتاة مثل هذه على فرصة
to earn her full human potential,
لتجد طاقاتها البشرية كاملة،
we have failed to become a truly moral and just human race.
نفشل في ان نكون مخلوقات أخلاقية عادلة.
Logistically speaking, it's incredibly possible
منطقيا، من السهل
to end extreme poverty.
أن ننهي مشكلة الفقر.
We just need to deliver proven goods and services
علينا فقط أن نوفر منتجات وخدمات جيدة
to everybody.
لكل شخص.
If we have the will, every one of us has a role to play.
لو عندنا الإرادة، لكل شخص دور يلعبه.
Let's deploy our time, our careers,
لنوظف وقتنا وجهدنا
our collective wealth.
وثرواتنا المتجمعة.
Let us deliver an end to extreme poverty
دعونا ننهي مشكلة الفقر
in this lifetime.
في تلك المرحة من الحياة.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)